黑客们你们好
hello hackers
我是Yan
I'm Yan
今天我们要讲的是沙盒
and today we're going to be talking about sandboxing
特别是chroot
specifically using chroot
chroot是什么？chroot是一种古老的技术
what is chroot well chroot is an old technique
这是操作系统的一部分
it's an old part of the operating system
它于1979年出现在Unix中
it appeared in Unix in 1979
很快就传到了BSD
shortly spread to BSD
并且从那时起传播到了所有的现代unix
and from there it spread to all of the modern Unixes
包括Linux
including Linux
我们会在Linux的背景下讨论它
and we'll be of course talking about it in the context of Linux
chroot所做的就是改变根目录的含义
what chroot does is change the meaning of slash
当你在普通的Linux系统中执行ls /
when you are in the normal Linux system and you do ls slash
这个/是文件系统的根目录
that is the root of your file system
Chroot会改变根的位置
chroot changes where that root is
它会将其设置到您指定的文件系统中的另一个目录
of course it sets it to another directory that is already on your file system that you specify
举个例子，如果你有一个jail目录
so for example if you had a jail
目录/tmp/jail
um directory in /tmp/jail
然后你使用chroot将它置为root
and you chrooted into that
任何在chroot中运行的进程
any process that runs inside that chroot so that
调用chroot的进程及其所有子进程将
the process that called chroot and all of its children would
会把/tmp/jail看作根目录
see a file system view that is rooted at /tmp/jail as opposed to the old /
那个年代的沙盒是这样的
this used to be the defacto way to sandbox
比如你想建一个web服务，那时候的人会说一定要在chroot中运行它
you'd set up a web server and I would say make sure to run it inside a chroot
你会发现它其实是一种弱的隔离机制
but as you'll see it it's kind of a weak um isolation metric
我们稍后会讲到这个
and we'll talk about that in a little later
我先展示一下chroot的效果
but first let me show you chroot
这是一个终端
so here we are on a terminal
Chroot实际上是shell上的一个实用程序
chroot is actually a utility on the shell
有一个
there's a
在Linux系统中默认安装
in Linux installed by default
/usr/sbin/chroot，它所做的只是调用/chroot，非常简单
/usr/sbin/chroot,  all it does is just call /chroot super simple
不好意思，它调用了chroot系统调用
or sorry it calls the chroot syscall
来把某个目录设置为根目录
to chroot you into somewhere
超级简单
super simple
可以用strace看一下
actually you can strace it
让我先
well let me first
我只是运行它
I just run it
我以root用户运行它
I'm running it as root
你必须有一定的权限才能运行chroot
um you have to have certain privileges to run chroot and by default uh
用户帐户
user accounts
普通用户没有这些权限
normal users do not have those privileges
正常情况下，你需要是root用户才能运行chroot
you need to be root normally to run chroot
所以我们要用sudo来运行
so we're gonna run it with sudo
chroot有两个参数
and chroot takes 2 arguments
一个是要chroot到的目录
one is the directory to chroot into
另一个是要在chroot下运行的命令（程序）
and the other one is the command
我会执行一个失败的操作
so I'm going to do something that won't work
我呆会会解释为什么
and I'll explain why
假如这个命令是bin bash，我们做了chroot
say bin bash okay so we did a chroot
将自己的根目录切换到/tmp/jail（在bash里切换bash的根目录）
chrooting ourselves into tmp jail
顺便说一下的chroot代表change root
chroot by the way I should have mentioned stands for change root
因此，我们将自己的根目录更改为/tmp/jail
so we're changing our root directory into /tmp/jail
我们还尝试运行/bin/bash
and we are trying to run /bin/bash
然后它说没有/bin/bash这个文件，这就很奇怪
and it's saying /bin/bash no such follow directory but that's weird
我明明可以ls /bin/bash. 它就在那儿
I can ls /bin/bash. it's right there
我可以运行/bin/bash
I can run /bin/bash
虽然我们会在递归中
I mean then we'll be in recur whatever
但你知道，它不存在是不可能的
but you know it doesn't make sense that it is not there
有趣的是
well the interesting thing is
在执行/bin/bash时
by the time we're executing this /bin/bash
我们其实是在/tmp/jail/中
we are inside the jail
这意味着
so this means
/bin/bash真正的意思是
that /bin/bash really means
/tmp/jail/bin/bash
但这并不存在
and that doesn't exist
我们的jail目录里到底有什么
so what does exist in our jail
我在视频开始前就设置好了
so I set this up right before the video
jail里有两个文件一个叫a
there are 2 files in the jail one is a file called a
另一个是busybox
the other one is busybox
什么是busybox busybox是一种
what isbusybox busybox is a um kind of
shell工具中的瑞士军刀
Swiss Army knife of shell utilities
这个忙碌箱是一个静态链接的二进制文件
this busybox is a statically linked binary
我给你们看这个是因为它很重要
I'm showing you this because that's important
chroot目录中没有库
there are no libraries inside the chroot
即使bin bash在chroot中
even if bin bash was inside the chroot
bin bash需要的所有库都不在那里
all of the libraries that bin bash needs aren't in there
那我还得把库也转过来
so I'd have to transfer the libraries as well
这真是让人头疼（大肠的一头）
and bin bash and it's a pain in the butt
但是你可以使用busybox，它非常简单
but you can use busybox and it is super easy
busybox附带了一系列不同的Linux实用程序的功能
busybox is um ships with the functionality of a bunch of different uh Linux utilities
在一些嵌入式设备中
in in in some embedded devices
Busybox是整个用户空间
busybox is the entire user space
这里基本上有你需要的一切
and there's basically everything you need here
有shell
there's a shell
有rm
there is uh you know things like R m uh
你可以查看主机名
you can check your host name
您可以关闭系统
you can shut down the system
你可以zip压缩等等
you can zip on zip etc
它的功能非常齐全
it's it's super feature complete
它的运作方式是
and the way it works is
运行它，通过ARG v 0或ARG v1告诉它
you basically run it and you tell it what either an ARG v 0 or an ARG v1
所以在这种情况下，它将是ARG v1
so in this case it will be an ARG v1
因为我只是从shell运行它
because I'm just running it from the shell
像往常一样，你告诉它你想执行什么程序
like normal you tell it what utility you wanted to execute
所以我执行sh，这是我的shell
so I do sh and here is my shell
现在我在busybox的自己的目录中
so now I am here in in my you know own directory in busybox
同样，我也可以执行Echo Hi等等
likewise I can do Echo Hi and and so forth
所以你可以做很多事情
right so you can do a lot of stuff
这基本上就是功能完整的用户空间
this is basically all you need for a functional userspace and
我们用它做一个演示环境
what we're using it for is a functional demo environment
让我们往回滚动
so let's scroll back up
然后执行这条语句
and do this
/tmp/jail/busybox
这样能成吗?
will this work
不能
no
首先，我们需要busybox sh
first of all of course we need busybox sh
但这行不通，因为
but it doesn't work because again
当在chroot环境下
when we're in the jail
这里第一个/实际上是指jail目录
when we say slash for the first /it actually means the jail
所以这条语句实际相当于/tmp/jail/tmp/jail/busybox
so what I'm trying to resolve here is actually equivalent to /tmp/jail/tmp/jail/busybox
当然这是不存在的
of course that doesn't exist
我们只有/tmp/jail/busybox
we just have /tmp/jail/busybox
我们怎么做呢?我们写/busybox
so how do we do this well we just say /busybox
这样就可以运行了
now this is gonna work
但是我的系统实际在根目录上并没有busybox
but there is no /busybox on my system right
这样执行是有效的
such busybox is valid inside the jail
是因为/tmp/jail/下存在busybox
because there is a /tmp/jail/busybox
好吧
okay
要点是当你chroot （参数1 参数2）的时候
just arriving to the point when you change root
对于参数2指定的命令，参数1指定的目录就是它的根目录
you end up in wherever you change rooted into and that is your new slash
现在你可以运行它了
so now you can run it all right
当然我们必须给它一个参数sh
of course we have to give it an argument sh
现在我们在一个shell中，被隔离在指定的/tmp/jail目录下
and now we are in a shell in isolation inside our new jail
如果我们执行busybox ls /
so if we do busybox ls /
这是我们的新根目录
here is our new root directory
而且
and
我们不能用很简单的方法离开这个目录
as I'll talk about we can't get out of this directory in very simple ways
在linux常规的cd .. 是行不通的
the same as on Linux we do /and then try to cd .. from there doesn't work
我们当然可以创建其他文件和目录
we can of course touch other files and directories
这也是为啥这会有个文件a
and that's how I ended up with a
我乱创的
I was playing around with this
现在我创建一个ASDF文件
so now I create an ASDF file
等我退出去证明给你们看
and let me prove to you that when I log out of here
在/tmp/jail中有我的ASDF文件
in /tmp/jail there is my ASDF file
但这里是在根目录
but here it was in slash
因为那是我的工作目录
because that was my working directory
这就是chroot的效果
um all right so that is how a chroot works
那么它的原理是怎样的
now what does it actually do well
Chroot是一个系统调用
chroot is a system call
它有两个效果
that has exactly 2 effects right
一是把根目录改成了指定的目录
one it changes the meaning of slash to whatever the jail is
二是它使得当你试着用../从这里出去时
and 2 it makes it so that when you try to dot dot /out of there
你最终还是在新根目录里
you end up still in jail
如果你的当前目录或
so if your current directory or
如果你输入../../../..在这个过程中碰到了/tmp/jail
if you go dot dot slash dot dot and at some point in that cycle you hit /tmp/jail
就停了，这样出不去的
you're screwed right you can't get out
它就做这两件事
that's all it does
它不会做任何其他奇异的事情，它不会关闭指向监狱外的文件描述符
it doesn't do any other exotic stuff it doesn't close file descriptors that you have pointing outside of the jail
它不会那样做
it doesn't do that
那些文件描述符仍然有效
those are still valid
它不会自动cd到新根目录下
it doesn't change directory into the jail
你必须自己手动做
you have to do that explicitly right
否则，您可能会处于一种情况，程序在jail目录中
otherwise you could end up in a situation where you are inside a directory
但你现在的工作目录在jail外面
your current working directory is outside of the jail
这很糟糕
and that's bad
因为拦截../的功能只适用于监狱内
because this catch of the dot dot only applies within the jail
它不做任何其他事情
it doesn't do anything else
这当然会引起问题
and so of course this causes problems
让我给你们看一个这样的问题
let me show you one such problem
这个问题的样子
that are what it looks like this problem
这是我写的chroot
so here is my chroot
我
I
这是
and this is
我写了一个chroot.c，它基本上等同于chroot命令
I wrote I wrote a chroot.c that is a replacement for basically the chroot utility
只不过我们用硬编码来运行busybox
except we're just hard coded to run busybox
你可以看到我正在chroot并将目录更改为/tmp/jail
and you can see I'm chrooting and changing directory into /tmp/jail
我来编译一下
let me compile this
好的，我运行sudo ./chroot
okay i run sudo ./chroot
现在我在jail里，和之前一模一样
and I am in jail and it's exactly as before
这里就是之前的jail
busybox ls / and here we are our old jail
好了，现在看一下如果我忘记更改目录会发生什么
all right now let me show you what happens if I forget to Change directory
oops，这不是C语言的注释方式
oops that's not how you comment in C
所以我只调用chroot然后执行
so I just chroot and execute
好吧
alright
编译，运行
compile that run it
好吧，我们马上就能看到奇怪的事情发生了
okay right away we see something weird is going on
之前有这个漂亮的提示符提示你现在所处的目录，还有想要执行的命令
before we have this nice prompt the directory you're in and then you know our command that we want to enter
现在getcwd说没有这样的文件或目录
now getcwd says no such filer or directory
这很奇怪
that's very weird
getcwd
先从这退出
let's log out here
是获取当前工作目录的系统调用
is the syscall that gets the current working directory
这是
well this is
这里填2
it's like there two
它是一个系统调用
it is a syscall
尽管它在man的第3节
even though it is giving it to us in section 3
它会得到当前的工作目录
so it gets the current working directory
就是这里，就是你现在所处的目录
that's this guy that's that's where you are right now
如果我这么做
if I do this
这里就是我当前的工作目录
you know that's my current working directory
它会得到当前的工作目录
so it gets the current working directory
但是很奇怪它竟然说没有这样的父目录
but it says something weird no such father directory
我的当前工作目录怎么可能不是父目录，这很奇怪
how can my current working directory not be a father directory right that's weird
另一个要注意的是这里的unknown
the other thing is as a result that says unknown here
好吧，我们来看看会发生什么
well let's see what happens when do
我一直在敲成baby是因为课后题叫babyshell
I keep typing baby as the babyshell for the challenges
当我们执行busybox ls的时候
when we do a busybox ls
执行结果看起来不像在jail里
that doesn't look like our jail
提醒一下，ls / 这样是在jail里
right as a reminder ls / this is our jail
但这样就不在jail里
but this this isn't our jail
这很奇怪
this is something weird
如果执行/busybox ls
what if you do ls
这显然是在PWN目录中
so this is in of course this pwn directory
退出看一下
let me just exit out of this
这就是这期视频用的工作目录
here it is it's my working directory for this video
如果在这执行ls
if I do ls here
哦，因为我现在在shell里
oh yeah because now that I'm in the shell
没问题
I am all good
我可以执行cd /
all right I can do cd /
现在变正常了
ls and now now things make sense again
现在我又回到jail里了
now I'm back in the jail
但如果我
but if I
当我刚进来的时候，我在一些奇怪的地方
when I first start in I am in some weird place
显然是在jail外
obviously outside of the jail
在我实际的目录中，也就是为这节课写材料的地方
in my actual home directory where I'm writing stuff for this lecture
如果我cd ../..
what if I CD dot dot /dot dot let's say
啊，这很有趣
ah that's interesting
现在我在另一个目录中，它的父目录的父目录
now I am in some other directory a parent of a parent of that
如果我一直回退下去
and if I go all the way out
最终会回到jail外文件系统的根目录
I am all the way back in the root directory of my file system which is outside of the jail
都是因为最开始就在jail外面
right all because I started out outside of the jail
因为没有调用chdir("/")
because there was no chroot
如果之后去到/tmp/jail目录，它立即就变成了根目录
if I then go and find /tmp/jail then suddenly I'm back in slash
因为现在我在监狱里，它知道该怎么做了
because now I'm inside the jail and it knows what to do
所以当你使用chroot时不改变目录就有问题了
so that's the tricky thing when you chroot and you don't change directory
还有其他几种会出错的情况
this is along with several other situations
我把视频移开
let me move my video out of the way there
这是chroot的缺陷之一
this is one of the pitfalls of chroot
一种情况是chroot时存在已打开的资源
one of the ways that things go wrong is there were previously opened resources before the chroot happened
例如当前工作目录
such as the current working directory
这是一种隐性的已打开资源
that is an implicitly open resource
在沙盒（chroot）中不受信任的代码获得控制权之前，这些资源并没有被关闭
and those resources were not closed or were not invalidated before um the untrusted code inside the sandbox inside the chroot got control um
你可以使用非常复杂的系统调用滥用这些之前打开的资源
you can abuse a lot of um these previously opened resources using pretty intricate system calls
像Linux中open和execve的at变体
and Linux for example the at variants of open and execve
这些变体不像open只需要一个路径或execve只需要一个二进制文件的路径
these variants unlike open which just takes a path or execve which just takes a path to a binary
openat接受已打开资源的文件描述符
openat takes a file descriptor of an open resource
和一条以这个资源为起点的相对路径
and a relative path from that
所以可以执行一个相对于之前打开的文件的程序
so you can say relative to some file that had previously been open execute a program
这会让你脱离chroot
and this bursts you out of the chroot
因为如果你在chroot之外有一个之前打开的资源
because if you have a previously open resource outside of the chroot
所有相对于它的东西都在chroot之外
then everything relative to that is still outside of the chroot
就像刚刚我们用busybox演示的那样
as we saw in my Journey Through busybox
同样的道理
the same way
就像我提到的
and like I mentioned
当前工作目录是一个隐式开放资源
the current working directory is an implicitly open resource
因此，当不受信代码获得控制权时，你的工作目录如果不在chroot中
so if your working directory is not in the chroot when the intrusted code gains control
那将是个问题
that is a problem
openat和execveat不是唯一可以被利用的
and openat and execveat are not the only thing that can be used
还有很多其他的变种
there are tons of other at variants
好了，我们来谈谈另一个问题：遗忘
all right let's roll on another problem forgetfulness
内核只为进程记录一个chroot
the kernel tracks one chroot for your process
如果你再次chroot
if you chroot again
它将覆盖之前的chroot
it'll override the previous chroot
所以如果你在choot中有root权限
so if you are running inside a chroot with root privileges
在本期作业中就有可能遇到这种情况
like you will in the homeworks in this assignment are the chance problems in this module rather
你可以再次chroot
you can just chroot again
覆盖掉之前chroot到的位置
and wipe out the old understanding of where the chroot jail used to be
好好思考如何用前面的概念来逃逸chroot
think through together with the previous concepts how can you use this to escape a chroot
这里总结一下
so kind of as a summary
chroot安全吗
is chroot safe
不安全，存在几个不同的原因
no I mean there are several different reasons
但一般来说，如果用户的eid为0
but generally speaking if a user with an effective ID of 0 so either
不论是suid程序，亦或有一个root程序，还是
a setuid binary or a said you had your root binary or
就是root用户在chroot中
just root is operating inside a chroot
除非chroot系统调用被阻塞，否则它们都可以逃逸
they can escape unless the chroot syscall is blocked
放在现在这不是一个很好的沙箱工具
it's not a goodsandboxing tool for in the kind of the modern way of doing things
但它是一个重要的历史性的工具，实际上现在也经常被使用
but it is an important historical one that is actually still frequently used
chroot的另一个缺点
another drawback of chroot
除了易逃脱，它还缺少了其他形式的隔离
other than the ability to escape is that it's missing other forms of isolation
让我来告诉你我的意思
let me show you what I mean by this
如果我chroot，即使我进了jail
if I chroot even if I go and and and happily go into my jail
现在我在jail里
so now I'm in my jail
一切都好，如果我
everything is good if I
好吧，你在这里看不到
ah well you can't see it here
有点偏离剧本，它有点难到我了
went a little off script and it bit me
嗯，我看看这里有netcat吗，没有
um let's see do I have netcat in this no
好吧
okay
你得相信我的话
uh you're gonna have to take my word for it
Um chroot不提供其他形式的隔离
um chroot does not provide other forms of isolation
所以它不提供进程ID隔离
right so it doesn't provide process ID isolation
举个例子，让我展示一个简单的验证方法
uh as an example actually let me show you an easy way to uh to look at this
我们执行一下chroot
let's let's um do our our chroot
先修复一下chroot，执行chdir
actually let's fix the chroot so does the ch directory
好的
all right
执行chroot
so we do our chroot
我们看看
we look at the
这会打印出这个shell的进程ID 13761
this echoes the process ID of the shell 13761
我要在另一个终端停止它
I'm gonna sig stop it in another terminal
不过你们看不到我在另一个终端的操作
so in another terminal that you can't see unfortunately
我会执行 kill -
I'm doing kill dash
SIGSTOP是多少来着
what is sig stop
kill -19 13761
dash 19 13761
好吧，我在另一个终端停止了这个shell
all right I stopped the shell in another terminal
好了，它在后台被停了
it's right it's it's it's still stopped in the background
可以用 ps aux 看到
I can psaux and I can see it
13761它与其他不同jail里的进程运行在相同的区域内
13761 it's running inside the same general isolation area as my other processes just in a different  jail
根据你的安全标准，这可能不是什么大问题，也可能是一个大问题
that might not be a big deal depending on your security criteria but but it could be a big deal
它在网络上也不是隔离的
it is not isolated on the network
例如，假如我在chroot中启动一个网络服务，它能使用
for example if I launch a network service inside the chroot it uses the
和chroot之外的网络服务相同的资源
same resources as network services outside of the chroot um
它也不是
it's not also
在与其他进程通信方面，它也不是孤立的
it's also not um isolated in terms of communicating with other processes
这些可能都是你想要强制隔离的安全属性
and so on this might all be security properties that you want to enforce the isolation of
所以它基本上，现在或多或少已经过时了
um and so it's it's basically um more or less obsoleted nowadays
它已经失宠了，嗯
it's fallen out of favor really um
实现快速系统隔离的现代方法是使用名称空间
the modern way of doing fast system isolation is with namespacing
我们将在本模块后续视频中讨论
we'll talk about that later in the module
另外还创建了新隔离措施
and additional isolation measures have been created
例如Cgroups和seccomp
such Cgroups and seccomp
这个我们也会讲到
and we'll talk about that as well
谢谢大家的聆听
thank you for listening
以后的视频见
and I'll see you in future videos